Guide to the Gately Family Photographs AIA.026
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gately Family Photographs
1846-1993
1880-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gately, Dermot, 1943-
AIA.026
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
This is a digital collection of 64 images contributed for research purposes by Dermot Gately, a professor of economics at New York University in 2000. Dermot Gately's great grandfather, Thomas Gately (1828–1905), emigrated from Ireland to New York City in 1847 and became an American citizen in 1854. This collection contains photographs of and some documents related to his descendents.
Custodial History
Original photographs were loaned to the Archives of Irish America in March of 2000. The photographs were scanned by NYU at 600 dpi and saved as TIFF files (IBM format). The original materials were returned to Dermot Gately. The accession number associated with this gift is 2000.017.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical Note
Thomas Gately (1828-1905), a native of Dublin, Ireland, was one of 11 children. As a child he lived with an uncle who was a draper, then in his teens shipped as a cabin boy on a sailing vessel. He emigrated to New York City around 1847. From 1850 to 1854 he worked at the Coolidge and Young distillery as the foreman of the rectifying floor, the stage at which a beverage's alcohol proof is adjusted by adding water or other liquids. He met Catherine Douglas (1835-1858), whose father owned a prosperous milk business. They were married in St. Mary's Church on Grand Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan on April 25, 1952 and eventually had three children: Margaret (1853-1854), Philip (1854-1948), and Joseph T. (1856-1905). On November 11, 1854 Gately became an American citizen.
In 1856 Gately was working as a distiller, compounder, and rectifier of spiritous liquors at the John Tracy and Co. plant in Albany, New York. During the Civil War he enlisted as a private in Company A of the 69th Regiment and fought at the Battle of Bull Run. He was honorably discharged on August 3, 1861. About seven years after the death of his first wife, Thomas Gately married Elizabeth Curran (1840-1879) in St. Joseph's Church in Albany on June 18, 1865. They had six children: Francis (1866-1932), Marcella (1868-1895), James (1870-1897), Thomas (1873-1918), Alphonsus (1875-1949), and Mary Elizabeth (1879).
Joseph T. Gately became a builder and contractor in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, specializing in masonry. On June 21, 1881 he married Catherine C. McQuillan (1856-1921) at St. Vincent de Paul's Church in Williamsburg. They had ten children: Irene "Rene" (1882-1974), Philip (1883-1906), Charles S. "Charlie," later Father Charles (1885-1917), Catherine "Kate" (1887-1954), Joseph "Joe" V. (1889-1961), Helen "Nell," later Sister Miriam Fidelis, 1891-1974), Thomas A. "Tom," later Father Thomas (1896-1996), Adrian C. (1898-1970), Rosemary C. (1900-1965), and Francis "Frank."
Adrian C. Gately spent his career in the Treasury Department of Consolidated Edison Company in New York City, retiring in 1964. His brother, Francis P. Gately also worked for the company. Adrian Gately married M. Loretta McDermott, a teacher, in 1939 and had two sons: Adrian C. and Dermot. Dermot became a professor of economics at NYU and has three children.
Source:
The preceding biographical information has been adapted from a history of the family written in 1975 by William A. Gately of New York City, relevant pages of which have been photocopied and are attached to the accession record.
Related Archival Materials
C.C. Gately Company Records (AIA 039)
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes 57 photographs of the Gately family, many dated from the 1880s through the 1960s. The photographs include portraits, group shots, business pictures, and informal photos of family members and gatherings documenting family events, vacations, and educational milestones. Of particular note is a picture of Kate McQuillan Gately with her class at P.S. 73 in Brooklyn, class photos from St. Vincent de Paul's school in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn and five photographs of Frank Gately related to his years at Consolidated Edison. Also included are copies of a handwritten note, an invitation to the Ordination to Priesthood of Charles S. Gately, letterhead from "Gately and Smith, Masons and Builders" and an 1846 baptismal certificate. Most items contain some descriptive information on the verso.
Arrangement
Photographs were assigned a digital identifier during the scanning process, which is noted on the reproductions. Files are listed alphabetically by their original digital identifiers.
New York (N.Y.).; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Irish Americans |z New York (State); Black-and-white photographs.; Digital images.; Curran, Irene Gately, 1882-1974; Gately, Kate McQuillan, 1856-1921; Gately, Adrian C., 1898-1970; Gately, Charles, 1885-1917; Gately, Joseph T., 1856-1905; Gately, Helen (Sr. Miriam Fidelis), 1891-1974; Gately, Thomas, 1828-1905.; Gately, Rosemary, 1900-1965; Gately and Smith, Masons and Builders; Leonard, Rosemary
- Gately and Smith, Masons and Builders letterhead, circa 1890s; cuid36398 (Box 1)
- C.C. Gately, Mason and Builder invoice, circa 1890s; cuid36399 (Box 1)
- Obverse of baby portrait showing the name and address of the photographer, undated; cuid36400 (Box 1)
- Photograph of four men at Frank Gately's retirement dinner, July 9, 1956; cuid36401 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Frank Gately giving a speech at his retirement dinner, July 9, 1956; cuid36402 (Box 1)
- Photograph of men on the Atlantic City Boardwalk, circa 1930s; cuid36403 (Box 1)
- Photograph of four men wearing boater hats on the Atlantic City Boardwalk, circa 1930s; cuid36404 (Box 1)
- Photograph of a class at St. Vincent de Paul's School in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, undated; cuid36405 (Box 1)
- Class portrait from P.S. 73, Brooklyn, undated; cuid36406 (Box 1)
- Family portrait tintype, circa 1890s; cuid36407 (Box 1)
- Family portrait tintype, circa 1890s; cuid36408 (Box 1)
- Portrait of woman, undated; cuid36409 (Box 1)
- Tintype portrait of children, circa 1890s; cuid36410 (Box 1)
- Outdoor family portrait, circa 1900; cuid36411 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Kate McQuinnon Gately and child, circa 1900; cuid36412 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Kate as a child, circa 1890s; cuid36413 (Box 1)
- Portrait of four children, circa 1910s; cuid36414 (Box 1)
- Portait of three men and three women, circa 1918; cuid36415 (Box 1)
- Photograph of a group seated at tables set up in a yard, undated; cuid36416 (Box 1)
- Photograph of six women sitting on a stoop, undated; cuid36417 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Irene Gately as an infant, 1883; cuid36418 (Box 1)
- Portrait of two men and a girl, undated; cuid36419 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Charlie as a boy, undated; cuid36420 (Box 1)
- Photograph of a man and woman laughing, undated; cuid36421 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Nell as a young woman, circa 1918; cuid36422 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Nell, undated; cuid36423 (Box 1)
- Letter to Frank from Nell written on College of St. Catherine letterhead, undated; cuid36424 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Frank Gately, circa 1960; cuid36425 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Frank Gately, circa 1930s; cuid36426 (Box 1)
- Photograph of a dancing couple, undated; cuid36427 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Thomas Gately, circa 1860s; cuid36428 (Box 1)
- Photograph of a couple kneeling at the alter during a wedding ceremony, undated; cuid36429 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Father Tom holding a baby, circa 1993; cuid36430 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Adrian Gately, circa 1920; cuid36431 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Adrian Gately outside of a house in Woodlawn, circa 1925; cuid36432 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Rene as a young woman with Rosemary as child, circa 1905; cuid36433 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Rosemary sitting on the stoop of a house in Woodlawn, Queens, September 19, 1925; cuid36434 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Rosemary and a man on the beach at Breezy Point, Queens, circa 1925-1930; cuid36435 (Box 1)
- Group photograph outside of a house in Woodhaven, Queens, February 13, 1921; cuid36436 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Mollie, Rosemary, and Kate [?] laughing, undated; cuid36437 (Box 1)
- Photograph of seven young women, undated; cuid36438 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Rosemary Leonard as a girl, undated; cuid36439 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Rosemary Leonard as a girl, undated; cuid36440 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Frank, Tom, and a woman on the beach at Breezy Point, Queens, undated; cuid36441 (Box 1)
- Tintype portrait of three men in an automobile, circa 1890; cuid36442 (Box 1)
- Tintype group portrait, circa 1898; cuid36443 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Joe in World War I military uniform, circa 1918; cuid36444 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Joseph Gately, circa 1880s; cuid36445 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Joseph Gately, circa 1900; cuid36446 (Box 1)
- Certificate of Renewal of Baptism Vows, 1846; cuid36447 (Box 1)
- Group portrait of four priests, undated; cuid36448 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Father Charles Gately, undated; cuid36449 (Box 1)
- Invitation to the ordination of Charles S. Gately in Baltimore Cathedral, June 21, 1911; cuid36450 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Charlie as a boy holding a rosary, undated; cuid36451 (Box 1)
- Portrait of Father Charles and another man sitting on a rock, undated; cuid36452 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Rosemary Gately, Sister Miriam Fidelis, and their aunt Mary McQuillan, undated; cuid36453 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Sister Miriam Fidelis holding baby Adrian, undated; cuid36454 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Sister Miriam Fidelis and Rosemary Leonard at the beach, undated; cuid36455 (Box 1)
- Hand colored photograph of Sister Miriam Fidelis in a garden, undated; cuid36456 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Rosemary Gately, Sister Miriam Fidelis, and Sister Rosemary Leonard, undated; cuid36457 (Box 1)
- Photograph of Rosemary Leonard wearing the habit of a postulant or novice nun, undated; cuid36458 (Box 1)